Guide to the Democratic Socialists of America Audiocassette Collection OH.058
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Democratic Socialists of America Audiocassette Collection
1976-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Democratic Socialists of America
OH.058
1.5 Linear Feet 2 cassette boxes, and 1 folder
69 audiocassettes
The Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) was founded in 1982. DSA promotes a socialist conception of democracy, with a key objective being the coalition-building of progressive groups in the United States. Michael Harrington (1928-1989) was a founder and leader of DSA from 1982-1989, and the founder and head of its predecessor, the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (1972-1982). The collection consists of 69 tapes, spanning the years 1976 - 1996, with the bulk of the items falling between the years 1985-1995. The majority of the audiocassettes consist of conference, convention and meeting recordings of the DSA, interviews and speeches of Michael Harrington, and programs and lectures that were either sponsored by, or featured members of, DSA.
Access Restrictions
Open to users without restriction.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were donated by the Democratic Socialists of America. The date of this donation is unknown. Materials in this collection were sarated from the Democratic Socialists of America Papers and established as their own collection in 2006. The accession numbers associated with these materials are 1980.017 and 2006.006. An additional 19 tapes from a 1980 conference were donated by Eli Kaminsky in 2014. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.150.
Arrangement
Alphabetically by series topic and chronologically thereunder.
Organized into the following subgroups: I. Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, series A as follows: A. Events; II. Democratic Socialists of America, 1982 - series A - C as follows: A. Meetings; B. Conferences; C. Programs; III. Harrington, Michael, - 1990, series A - D as follows: A. Debates; B. Interviews; C. Programs, D. Speeches and Lectures; IV. Miscellaneous, series A - C as follows: A. Interviews; B. Programs; C. Speeches and Lectures.
Series:
Part 1: Series A: Events
Part 2: Series A: Events
Part 2: Series B: Conferences
Part 2: Series C: Programs
Part 3: Series A: Debates
Part 3: Series B: Interviews
Part 3: Series C: Programs
Part 3: Series D: Speeches and Lectures
Part 4: Series A: Interviews
Part 4: Series B: Programs
Part 4: Series C: Speeches and Lectures
Historical/Biographical Note
The Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) was formed in 1982 after a merger of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and the New American Movement (NAM). DSOC was formed in 1973 by a split in the Social Democrats USA; NAM was organized in 1971 by New Leftists. As a unified group, the DSA's ideology is based on a socialist conception of democracy. A key objective is to build a coalition of the major progressive forces in the United States, including trade unions, women's groups and minority organizations. Its tactics include grass-roots activity, working within existing mainstream institutions, and electoral politics within the left wing of the Democratic Party. The DSA is the U.S. affiliate to the Socialist International.
The structure of the DSA parallels that of the former DSOC. The decision-making bodies of the DSA consist of: the National Convention, which meets biennially; the National Board (NB), which meets between National Conventions and has the authority to charter local and regional organizations; the National Executive Committee (NEC), which meets between the National Boards and National conventions; and the National Interim Committee (NIC), a subcommittee of the NEC which meets between meetings of the NEC and is responsible for the supervision of all offices and staff of the organization. The National Board charters a Youth Section for full-time students age 30 and younger, which has its own locals and structured organization. The NB or the NEC can charter commissions. Members of the NEC serve as liaisons to the commissions and locals and can appoint committees (such as the NIC). Local and regional organizations, chartered by the NEC, carry out independent activities throughout the country.
Michael Harrington (1928-1989) was a U.S. socialist, editor, writer, founder and leader of DSA, and political leader best known for his book The Other America: Poverty in the United States 1962).
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Michael Harrington Papers (TAM 209)
Michael Harrington - DSA Audiotapes (OH 048)
Democratic Socialists of America Records (TAM 105)
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 69 tapes, spanning the years 1976 - 1996, with the bulk of the items falling between 1985 - 1995. The majority of the audiocassettes consist of conference, convention and meeting recordings of the DSA, interviews and speeches of Michael Harrington, and programs and lectures that were either sponsored by, or featured members of, DSA. Many of the recordings feature or refer to DSA Co-Chairs Michael Harrington and Barbara Ehrenreich.
The collection has been divided into four subgroups: DSOC, DSA, Michael Harrington, and Miscellaneous. Subgroup One (DSOC) contains a recording of a rally sponsored by the Democratic Agenda Project, which was a joint venture between the DSOC and various progressive groups. Subgroup Two (DSA) contains organizational recordings of DSA, including conferences, meetings and sponsored programs. Subgroup Three (Michael Harrington) contains interviews, speeches and debates featuring Michael Harrington, some of which predate the founding of DSA (1982). Subgroup Four contains miscellaneous audiocassettes, some of which feature DSA members, but the majority whose contents or relationship to DSA are unidentified.
Conference recordings added to the collection in 2017 include 19 audiocassettes and a conference schedule from the the 1980 Institute for Democratic Socialism Conference "Eurosocialism and America: An International Exchange".
Separated Material
A letter from the Political Science Department at Loyola University of Chicago to Michael Harrington regarding a lecture was removed from the collection.
Socialism -- United States -- Interviews.; Socialism -- United States.; Audiocassettes; Right and left (Political science); Radicalism -- United States.; Labor movement -- United States.; Labor -- United States.; Alperovitz, Gar; Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.); Ehrenreich, Barbara; Democratic Socialists of America; Aronowitz, Stanley; Bahr, Morton; Committee in Solidarity with the People of El Salvador (U.S.); Cosell, Howard, 1918-1995; Kemp, Jack.; United Steelworkers of America; Harvard Union of Clerical and Technical Workers; Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989 -- |v Interviews; Meyerson, Harold .; Lerner, Michael, 1943-; Gordon, David M.; Fitrakis, Robert J., 1955-; Steinem, Gloria.; Williams, Lynn R.; West, Cornel; Piven, Frances Fox; Nadler, Jerrold; Socialist International (1951- ); Schwartz, Joseph.
- Series I: Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, 1980
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series related to the "Eurosocialism and America" conference include a copy of the conference program and recordings of conference panels and plenary speeches. Not all panels from the conference were recorded. The printed conference schedule contains a full list of panels and speakers, with annotations indicating which sessions are included in the recordings. Notable individuals featured in the recordings include world leaders like Willy Brandt (Germany), Olof Palme (Sweden), Joop den Uyl (Netherlands), Francois Mitterand (France), as well as Michael Harrington, union leader William Winpisinger, Representative Ron Dellums, and Gloria Steinem.
  - Sub-series A: Events.
    - Democratic Agenda Rally, August 15, 1980; cuid268 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-1, Box OH Shared Access Box 2, Cd OH 58-1)
    - Eurosocialism and America: An International Exchange Conference Recordings, 1980 December 5-7 (Box 2)
    - Eurosocialism and America: An International Exchange Conference Schedule, 1980 December 5-7 (Box MS002, Folder 1)
- Series II: Democratic Socialists of America, 1984-1992
  - Sub-series A: Conferences.
    - New Directions Conference, 1986; cuid269 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-2, Box OH Shared Access Box 2, Cd OH 58-2)
      General note
      Speakers include Barbara Ehrenreich, Michael Harrington and Lynn R. Williams of the United Steelworkers of America.
    - Democratic Alternatives Conference (1987: Albany, N.Y.), Feb 27, 1987 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-3)
      Speakers include Robert Lekachman, Barbara Ehrenreich, Michael Harrington. Moderator: Jo-Ann Mort.
    - Socialist Scholars Conference (1991: New York, N.Y.) - 2 tapes, April 6, 1991 April 7, 1991 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-4 a-b)
    - DSA National Convention 1993 - 10 tapes, Nov 12, 1993 Nov 13, 1993 Nov 14, 1993 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-5 a-j)
      "Politics in the Clinton Era". Cornel West speaks.
    - Socialist Scholars Conference (1995) - 5 tapes, April 7, 1995 April 8, 1995 April 9, 1995 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-6 a-e)
      Speakers include Stanley Aronowitz, Jorge Calderon, Bogdan Denitch, David Gordon and Frances Fox Piven.
  - Sub-series B: Meetings.
    - National Executive Committee - 3 tapes, Jun 2, 1984 Jun 3, 1984 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-7 a-c)
      Barbara Ehrenreich speaks.
    - National Board Meeting (1988: Los Angeles, CA), Nov 10, 1988 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-8)
      Speakers include Charlie Degamond, Barbara Ehrenreich, Michael Harrington and Harold Meyerson.
    - National Board Leadership School - 2 tapes, Jun 12, 1992 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-9 a-b)
      Question and answer period with with Gar Alperowitz.
    - DSA's Domestic Agenda, no date; cuid270 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-10, Box OH Shared Access Box 2, Cd OH 58-10 A-B)
  - Sub-series C: Programs.
    - Paul Pinsky, Mary Jo Kilroy, David Kusnick and Bob Fitrakis, Jun 14, 1992 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-11)
    - Frances Fox Piven:Women in the Welfare State(1995: Portland, ME), Mar 10, 1995 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-12)
    - Michael Lerner and Cornel West.Jews and Blacks: Let the healing/future begin(1995: Cambridge, Mass.), April 24, 1995 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-13)
    - Cornel West, Kurt Stand, Heidi Hartman and Bob Fitrakis, 1995 or 1996 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-14)
- Series III: Michael Harrington, 1976-1989
  - Sub-series A: Debates.
    - Michael Harrington debates David Rockefeller, VP of Chase Manhattan Bank, 1976; cuid271 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-15, Box OH Shared Access Box 2, Cd OH 58-15 A-B)
    - Michael Harrington debates Rep. Jack Kemp (New York, NY), April 25, 1979 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-16)
      Tax Policy and the Economy
  - Sub-series B: Interviews.
    - 8/2/88- tape II, Aug 02, 1988 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-17)
    - Howard Cosell interviews Michael Harrington, Aug 19, 1988 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-18)
  - Sub-series C: Programs.
    - Michael Harrington: In His Own Words., no date; cuid272 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-19, Box OH Shared Access Box 2, Cd OH 58-19)
    - Michael Harrington Remembrance on NPR's Morning Edition, Aug 2, 1989 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-20)
  - Sub-series D: Speeches and Lectures.
    - Unidentified Conference (Chicago, Ill.), late 1970s (Box 1, Folder OH 58-21)
    - American Public Health Association (APHA) Convention - 2 tapes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-22 a-b)
    - Lecture at Department of Political Science at Loyola University of Chicago - 2 tapes, 1985 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-23 a-b)
    - Jewish Labor Board Luncheon (1987: New York, NY), , Oct 15, 1987 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-24)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous, 1988-1995
  - Sub-series A: Interviews.
    - Kris Rondeau of Harvard Clerical and Technical Workers Union, June 13, 1988; cuid273 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-25, Box OH Shared Access Box 2, Cd OH 58-25)
  - Sub-series B: Programs.
    - Ellen Braune and Cajuste Lexiuste on Haiti - CISPES, July 20, 1994 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-26)
    - Federal Judge denies FCC injunction against micro-radio, Jan 20, 1995 (Box 1, Folder OH 58-27)
      Original program produced by San Francisco Liberation Radio.
    - Untitled (labeled "opening session, afternoon session. Ind. Dem."), undated (Box 1, Folder OH 58-28)
  - Sub-series C: Speeches and Lectures.
    - Shakoor on multiculturalism, Suzanne Crowell on mission, undated (Box 1, Folder OH 58-29)
    - Joe Schwartz on identity politics., undated (Box 1, Folder OH 58-30)
    - Frances Fox Piven, Morton Bahr and Gloria Steinem, undated (Box 1, Folder OH 58-31)